I need to start by telling you a little bit
في البداية أود أن أحدثكم قليلًا
about my social life,
عن حياتي الاجتماعية،
which I know may not seem relevant,
والتي أعلم أنها تبدو غير ذات علاقة بالموضوع،
but it is.
ولكنها كذلك.
When people meet me at parties
عندما يقابلني الناس في الحفلات
and they find out that I'm an English professor
ويعلمون أنني بروفيسورة في اللغة الإنجليزية
who specializes in language,
ومتخصصة فيها،
they generally have one of two reactions.
عادةً ما تكون ردة فعلهم واحدة من اثنتين.
One set of people look frightened. (Laughter)
مجموعة منهم تشعر بالخوف. (ضحك)
They often say something like,
غالبًا ما يقولون شيئًا كـ،
"Oh, I'd better be careful what I say.
" أوه، يستحسن بي أن أنتبه لما أقوله.
I'm sure you'll hear every mistake I make."
أنا متأكد بأنك ستسمعين كل الأخطاء التي أرتكبها."
And then they stop talking. (Laughter)
وبعدها يتوقفون عن الكلام. (ضحك)
And they wait for me to go away
وينتظرون حتى أذهب بعيدًا
and talk to someone else.
لأتكلم مع أحد غيرهم.
The other set of people,
المجموعة الأخرى من الناس،
their eyes light up,
تشع عيونهم،
and they say,
ويقولون،
"You are just the person I want to talk to."
" أنتِ الشخص الذي نوّد التحدث معه."
And then they tell me about whatever it is
وبعدها يبدؤون بإخباري عن كل شيء
they think is going wrong with the English language.
يعتقدون أنه خاطئ في اللغة الإنجليزية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A couple of weeks ago, I was at a dinner party
قبل عدة أسابيع، كنت في حفلة عشاء
and the man to my right
وبدأ الرجل الذي على يميني
started telling me about all the ways
بإخباري عن كل الطرق
that the Internet is degrading the English language.
التي يهين بها الإنترنت اللغة الإنجليزية.
He brought up Facebook, and he said,
وذكر الفيسبوك كمثال، ثم قال،
"To defriend? I mean, is that even a real word?"
" دي- فريند؟ أعني، هل تلك أصلًا كلمة حقيقية؟"
I want to pause on that question:
أريد أن أتوقف عند هذا السؤال:
What makes a word real?
ما الذي يجعل الكلمة حقيقية؟
My dinner companion and I both know
أنا وزميلي في العشاء، كلانا يعلم
what the verb "defriend" means,
ما تعنيه كلمة "دي-فريند"،
so when does a new word like "defriend"
متى تصبح كلمة جديدة مثل "دي-فريند"
become real?
كلمة حقيقية؟
Who has the authority to make those kinds
من الذي يمتلك الصلاحية لاتخاذ مثل هذه
of official decisions about words, anyway?
القرارات الرسمية عن الكلمات، على أية حال؟
Those are the questions I want to talk about today.
تلك هي الأسئلة التي أود الحديث عنها اليوم.
I think most people, when they say a word isn't real,
أعتقد أن أغلب الناس، عندما يقولون أن الكلمة غير حقيقية،
what they mean is, it doesn't appear
فهم يقصدون أنها لا تظهر
in a standard dictionary.
في المعاجم العادية.
That, of course, raises a host of other questions,
وإن ذلك بالطبع يثير عدة تساؤلات،
including, who writes dictionaries?
بما فيها، من الذي يكتب المعاجم؟
Before I go any further,
قبل أن أسترسل في الأمر،
let me clarify my role in all of this.
دعوني أوضح دوري في كل هذا.
I do not write dictionaries.
أنا لا أكتب المعاجم.
I do, however, collect new words
أنا، على أية حال، أجمع الكلمات الجديدة
much the way dictionary editors do,
بطريقة مشابهة جدًا للتي يتبعها محرر القاموس،
and the great thing about being a historian
وإن الشيء الرائع بخصوص كوني مؤرخًة
of the English language
للغة الإنجليزية
is that I get to call this "research."
هو أني أستطيع أن أطلق على هذا "بحث".
When I teach the history of the English language,
عندما أقوم بتدريس تاريخ اللغة الإنجليزية،
I require that students teach me
أطلب أن يعلمني التلاميذ
two new slang words before I will begin class.
اثنتين من الكلمات العامية الجديدة قبل أن أبدأ بالمحاضرة.
Over the years, I have learned
وقد تعلمت على مدار السنوات
some great new slang this way,
بعض الكلمات العامية الرائعة والجديدة بهذه الطريقة
including "hangry," which --
بما فيها "هانغري" وهي --
(Applause) —
(تصفيق) --
which is when you are cranky or angry
وهي عندما تكون غريب الأطوار أو عصبيًا
because you are hungry,
لأنك جائع.
and "adorkable,"
و"أدروكابل"،
which is when you are adorable
وهي عندما تكون رائعًا
in kind of a dorky way,
بطريقة غبية نوعًا ما،
clearly, terrific words that fill
إنها بصراحة كلمات رائعة تملأ
important gaps in the English language.
الفجوات المهمة في اللغة الإنجليزية.
(Laughter)
(َضحك)
But how real are they
لكن ما مدى حقيقة هذه الكلمات
if we use them primarily as slang
إن استخدمناها بشكل أساسي ككلمات عامية
and they don't yet appear in a dictionary?
وهي لا تظهر للآن في القاموس؟
With that, let's turn to dictionaries.
وبهذا، دعونا نذهب للقواميس.
I'm going to do this as a show of hands:
سأقوم بهذا كتصويت بالأيدي:
How many of you still regularly
كم منكم لا زالوا معتادين
refer to a dictionary, either print or online?
على الرجوع إلى القاموس، سواء المطبوع أو على الانترنت؟
Okay, so that looks like most of you.
حسنًا، إذن يبدو أن معظمكم يفعل ذلك.
Now, a second question. Again, a show of hands:
الآن، سؤال ثانٍ. مرة أخرى تصويت بالأيدي:
How many of you have ever looked to see
كم واحد منكم سبق وأن نظر ليرى
who edited the dictionary you are using?
من قام بتحرير القاموس الذي يستخدمه؟
Okay, many fewer.
حسنًا، أقل بكثير.
At some level, we know that there are human hands
إلى حد ما، نعرف بأن هناك أشخاصًا
behind dictionaries,
خلف صناعة القواميس،
but we're really not sure who those hands belong to.
ولكننا حقًا لسنا متأكدين من هم هؤلاء.
I'm actually fascinated by this.
أنا مندهشة بالفعل لهذا.
Even the most critical people out there
حتى أن أكثر الناس نقدًا
tend not to be very critical about dictionaries,
يميلون إلى ألا يكونوا متشددين بخصوص القواميس،
not distinguishing among them
لا يميزون بينها
and not asking a whole lot of questions
ولا يسألون الكثير من الأسئلة
about who edited them.
عن الذين قاموا بتحريرها.
Just think about the phrase
فكّر فقط في العبارة
"Look it up in the dictionary,"
"ابحث عنها في القاموس،"
which suggests that all dictionaries
والتي تقترح أن كل القواميس
are exactly the same.
هي متشابهة تمامًا.
Consider the library here on campus,
خذ المكتبة هنا التي في حرم الجامعة بعين الاعتبار،
where you go into the reading room,
حيث أنك تدخل إلى غرفة القراءة،
and there is a large, unabridged dictionary
وهناك قاموس كبير غير مختصر
up on a pedestal in this place of honor and respect
مرفوع على قاعدة في مكان للشرف والاحترام
lying open so we can go stand before it
ويقبع مفتوحًا حتى نستطيع الوقوف أمامه
to get answers.
لأخذ الإجابات.
Now, don't get me wrong,
الآن، لا تفهموني خطئًا،
dictionaries are fantastic resources,
إن القواميس مصادر رائعة،
but they are human
ولكنها إنسانية
and they are not timeless.
وليست خالدة.
I'm struck as a teacher
أنا مصعوقة كمعلمة
that we tell students to critically question
من أننا نقول للتلاميذ بأن يقرؤوا قراءة نقدية
every text they read, every website they visit,
كل نص يقرؤونه، وكل موقع إلكتروني يزورونه،
except dictionaries,
عدا القواميس،
which we tend to treat as un-authored,
والتي نميل إلى معاملتها على أنها غير مؤلفة،
as if they came from nowhere to give us answers
كما لو أنها أتت من عالم آخر لتعطينا الإجابات
about what words really mean.
عما تعنيه الكلمات في حقيقتها.
Here's the thing: If you ask dictionary editors,
انظروا معي: لو سألتم محرري القاموس،
what they'll tell you
ما سيقولونه لكم
is they're just trying to keep up with us
هو أنهم فقط يحاولون مجاراتنا
as we change the language.
بينما نغير نحن اللغة.
They're watching what we say and what we write
هم يراقبون ما نقوله وما نكتبه
and trying to figure out what's going to stick
ويحاولون تحديد ما سوف يعلق
and what's not going to stick.
وما لن يعلق.
They have to gamble,
عليهم المقامرة،
because they want to appear cutting edge
لأنهم يريدون أن يظهروا على أنهم متطورين
and catch the words that are going to make it,
ويمسكوا الكلمات التي يريدون أن يصنعوها،
such as LOL,
مثل "لول"،
but they don't want to appear faddish
ولكنهم لا يريدون أن يظهروا على أنهم تابعو صيحات
and include the words that aren't going to make it,
ويضمنوا الكلمات التي لن تستطيع النجاة،
and I think a word that they're watching right now
وأعتقد أن الكلمة التي يراقبونها الآن حالًا
is YOLO, you only live once.
هي "يولو"، أنت تعيش فقط لمرة واحدة.
Now I get to hang out with dictionary editors,
الآن عليّ أن أخرج مع محرري القواميس،
and you might be surprised
ولربما تتفاجأ
by one of the places where we hang out.
من أحد الأماكن التي نخرج إليها.
Every January, we go
في كل يناير، نذهب إلى
to the American Dialect Society annual meeting,
الاجتماع السنوي لجمعية اللهجة الأمريكية،
where among other things,
حيث بين العديد من الأمور،
we vote on the word of the year.
نقوم بالتصويت على كلمة العام.
There are about 200 or 300 people who come,
هنالك حوالي 200 أو 300 شخص يأتون،
some of the best known linguists in the United States.
بعضهم من أشهر اللغويين في الولايات المتحدة.
To give you a sense of the flavor of the meeting,
ولإعطائكم نبذة عن نكهة اللقاء،
it occurs right before happy hour.
فإنه يحدث بالضبط قبل الساعة السعيدة.
Anyone who comes can vote.
بإمكان أي شخص يأتي أن يقوم بالتصويت.
The most important rule is
الشرط الأهم هو
that you can vote with only one hand.
أن بإمكانك أن تصوت بيد واحدة فقط.
In the past, some of the winners have been
في الماضي، قد كانت بعض الكلمات الفائزة
"tweet" in 2009
"تويت" في 2009
and "hashtag" in 2012.
"هاشتاغ" في 2012.
"Chad" was the word of the year in the year 2000,
وكانت "تشاد" هي كلمة العام لسنة 2000،
because who knew what a chad was before 2000,
لأنه من يعلم ماذا كانت تشاد قبل سنة 2000،
and "WMD" in 2002.
و"دبليو إم دي" في 2002.
Now, we have other categories in which we vote too,
لدينا تصنيفات أخرى نقوم بالتصويت فيها أيضًا،
and my favorite category
والتصنيف المفضل لديّ
is most creative word of the year.
وكلمة العام الأكثر إبداعية.
Past winners in this category have included
تضمنت الكلمات الفائزة السابقة في هذا التصنيف
"recombobulation area,"
"ركومبوبيوليشن آريا"،
which is at the Milwaukee Airport after security,
والتي تتواجد في مطار مواكي بعد قسم الأمن،
where you can recombobulate.
حيث بإمكانك أن ريكمبيوليت!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can put your belt back on,
بإمكانك أن تعيد ارتداء حزامك،
put your computer back in your bag.
وأن تعيد وضع حاسوبك في حقيبتك.
And then my all-time favorite word at this vote,
وبعد ذلك فإن الكلمة المفضلة لدي دومًا في هذا التصويت،
which is "multi-slacking."
وهي "ملتي - سلاكنج".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And multi-slacking is the act
إن ملتي - سلاكنج هو الحدث
of having multiple windows up on your screen
حيث تمتلك عدة نوافذ ظاهرة على شاشتك
so it looks like you're working
حيث يبدو بأنك تعمل
when you're actually goofing around on the web.
بينما أنت متورط برسائل الخطأ في الإنترنت.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Will all of these words stick? Absolutely not.
حسنًا هل تبقى هذه الكلمات؟ بالتأكيد لا.
And we have made some questionable choices,
لقد قمنا ببعض الاختيارات المشكوك بها،
for example in 2006
على سبيل المثال في عام 2006
when the word of the year was "Plutoed,"
عندما كانت كلمة العام هي "بلوتود"
to mean demoted.
وتعني يحط مرتبته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But some of the past winners
ولكن بعض الكلمات الفائزة السابقة
now seem completely unremarkable,
تبدو الآن عادية بالكامل،
such as "app"
مثل "آب"
and "e" as a prefix,
و"إي" كبادئة،
and "google" as a verb.
و"جوجل" كفعل.
Now, a few weeks before our vote,
الآن، قبل أسابيع من تصويتنا،
Lake Superior State University
تصدر جامعة ليك سوبيريور ستيت
issues its list of banished words for the year.
قائمتها من الكلمات المتهالكة للعام.
What is striking about this
المدهش بهذا الشأن
is that there's actually often quite a lot of overlap
هو أن هناك في الغالب كثير من التداخل
between their list and the list that we are considering
بين قائمتها وتلك التي نضعها في عين الاعتبار
for words of the year,
لكلمات العام،
and this is because we're noticing the same thing.
وهذا لأننا نلاحظ نفس الشيء.
We're noticing words that are coming into prominence.
نلاحظ كلمات تخرج إلى العالم.
It's really a question of attitude.
إنها حقًا مسألة موقف.
Are you bothered by language fads and language change,
هل أنت منزعج بسبب البدع اللغوية والتغيرات في اللغة،
or do you find it fun, interesting,
أم أنك تجدها ممتعة، مثيرة للاهتمام،
something worthy of study
شيء يستحق الدراسة
as part of a living language?
كجزء من لغة حية؟
The list by Lake Superior State University
إن قائمة جامعة ليك سوبيريور ستيت
continues a fairly long tradition in English
تستمر في تقليد قديم نوعًا ما في الإنجليزية
of complaints about new words.
من الشكوى بشأن الكلمات الجديدة.
So here is Dean Henry Alford in 1875,
إذن هنا العميد هنري ألفورد عام 1875،
who was very concerned that "desirability"
والذي كان قلقًا جدًا من أن "دزيرابلتي"
is really a terrible word.
هي كلمة فظيعة حقًا.
In 1760, Benjamin Franklin
وفي 1760، كتب بنجامين فرانكلين
wrote a letter to David Hume
رسالة إلى ديفيد هيوم
giving up the word "colonize" as bad.
يعترض على كلمة "كولونايز" ككلمة سيئة.
Over the years, we've also seen worries
وعبر السنين، رأينا أيضًا مخاوف
about new pronunciations.
بشأن طرق جديدة للنطق.
Here is Samuel Rogers in 1855
هنا صموئيل روجرز في 1855
who is concerned about some fashionable pronunciations
وهو قلق إزاء بعض الكلمات المنطوقة الحديثة
that he finds offensive,
والتي يراها عدوانية،
and he says "as if contemplate were not bad enough,
إذ يقول "كأن التأمل ليس سيئًا كفاية،
balcony makes me sick."
تجعلني الشرفة أشعر بالاستياء."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The word is borrowed in from Italian
هذه الكلمة مستعارة من الإيطالية
and it was pronounced bal-COE-nee.
وقد كانت تنطق بال-كو-ني.
These complaints now strike us as quaint,
هذه التناقضات تخطر لنا الآن بطريقة غريبة وجذابة،
if not downright adorkable -- (Laughter) --
إن لم تكن أدروكابل -- (ضحك) --
but here's the thing:
ولكن ها هو الأمر:
we still get quite worked up about language change.
لا زلنا متحمسين نوعًا ما بشأن تغيرات اللغة.
I have an entire file in my office
لديّ ملف كامل في مكتبي
of newspaper articles
من مقالات الصحف
which express concern about illegitimate words
التي تعبر عن قلق بشأن الكلمات غير المنطقية
that should not have been included in the dictionary,
والتي كان ينبغي عدم تضمينها في القاموس،
including "LOL"
بما في ذلك "لول"
when it got into the Oxford English Dictionary
عندما أدرجت في قاموس أكسفورد للإنجليزية
and "defriend"
و"ديفرند"
when it got into the Oxford American Dictionary.
عندما أدرجت في قاموس أكسفورد للإنجليزية الأمريكية.
I also have articles expressing concern
لديّ أيضًا مقالات تعبر عن القلق
about "invite" as a noun,
بشأن "إنفايت" كإسم،
"impact" as a verb,
و"إمباكت" كفعل،
because only teeth can be impacted,
لأن الأسنان فقط هي التي يمكن رصها
and "incentivize" is described
والـ "إنسنتفايز" هي التي يمكن وصفها
as "boorish, bureaucratic misspeak."
كـ "كلمات فظة وأخطاء كلامية بيروقراطية."
Now, it's not that dictionary editors
الآن، ليس أن محرري القواميس
ignore these kinds of attitudes about language.
يتجاهلون هذه الأنواع من المواقف حول اللغة.
They try to provide us some guidance about words
فهم يحاولون تزودينا بقليل من التوجيه بخصوص الكلمات
that are considered slang or informal
التي تعتبر عامية وغير رسمية
or offensive, often through usage labels,
أو عدوانية، غالبًا من خلال إطار استعمالها،
but they're in something of a bind,
لكنهم في نوع من الاتفاق،
because they're trying to describe what we do,
لأنهم يحاولون وصف ما نفعله،
and they know that we often go to dictionaries
وهم يعلمون أننا غالبًا ما نذهب إلى القواميس
to get information about how we should use a word
كي نحصل على معلومات عن كيف يجب استخدام كلمة
well or appropriately.
بشكل صحيح أو على نحو مناسب.
In response, the American Heritage Dictionaries
واستجابة لذلك، تحتوي قواميس أميريكان هيرتيج
include usage notes.
على ارشادات استخدام.
Usage notes tend to occur with words
غالبًا ما تأتي ارشادات الاستخدام مع الكلمات
that are troublesome in one way,
المسببة للمشاكل بطريقة ما،
and one of the ways that they can be troublesome
وأحد هذه الطرق التي تمكنها من أن تصبح مسببة للمشاكل
is that they're changing meaning.
أنها تغير المعنى.
Now usage notes involve very human decisions,
إرشادات الاستخدام تتضمن قرارات بشرية فعلية،
and I think, as dictionary users,
وأنا أعتقد، كمستخدمين للقاموس،
we're often not as aware of those human decisions
فإننا غالبًا لسنا ندرك هذه القرارات الإنسانية
as we should be.
كما ينبغي أن نكون.
To show you what I mean,
ولأريكم ما أعنيه،
we'll look at an example, but before we do,
سننظر إلى مثال، ولكن قبل أن نفعل ذلك،
I want to explain what the dictionary editors
أود أن أشرح ما يحاول محررو القواميس
are trying to deal with in this usage note.
التعامل معه بملاحظة الاستخدام هذه.
Think about the word "peruse"
فكر في كلمة "برسيو"
and how you use that word.
وكيف تستخدم تلك الكلمة.
I would guess many of you are thinking
أظن بأن الكثير منكم يفكرون
of skim, scan, reading quickly.
بتقليب الصفحات والفحص الدقيق والقراءة السريعة.
Some of you may even have some walking involved,
ربما يكون للبعض منكم شيء من المشي متداخلًا مع الموضوع،
because you're perusing grocery store shelves,
لأنكم تتفحصون في رفوق متجر الخضار،
or something like that.
أو شيء مشابه.
You might be surprised to learn
من الممكن أن تفاجئوا بأن تعلموا
that if you look in most standard dictionaries,
بأنكم إن نظرتم في القواميس الأكثر معيارية،
the first definition will be to read carefully,
فإن أول تعريف ستقرؤونه هو القراءة بعناية،
or pore over.
أو يصب على.
American Heritage has that as the first definition.
أميريكان هيريتيج يحوي ذلك كأول تعريف.
They then have, as the second definition, skim,
ثم يوجد لديهم، كتعريف ثان، تقليب الصفحات،
and next to that, they say "usage problem."
ثم بجانبها يقولون "مشكة في الاستعمال."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then they include a usage note,
ثم يرفقون بها ملاحظة استخدام،
which is worth looking at.
تستحق النظر إليها.
So here's the usage note:
إذن ها هي ملاحظة الاستخدام:
"Peruse has long meant 'to read thoroughly'...
"اعتدنا لفترة طويلة أن نقرأ برسو بشكل كامل"...
But the word is often used more loosely,
ولكن الكلمة إذا ما تم استخدمها أغلب الأحيان بشكل أكثر عمومية،
to mean simply 'to read.'...
لكي تعني ببساطة "أن تقرأ"...
Further extension of the word to mean 'to glance over, skim,'
والامتداد الآخر للكلمة كي تعني "أتصفح"
has traditionally been considered an error,
تم اعتباره خطئًا بطريقة تقليدية،
but our ballot results suggest that it is becoming
ولكن نتائج اقتراعنا توحي بأنه يصبح
somewhat more acceptable.
مقبولًا نوعًا ما.
When asked about the sentence,
وعند السؤال عن الجملة،
'I only had a moment to peruse the manual quickly,'
"كان لدي القليل من الوقت لتصفح دليل الاستخدام بسرعة"
66 percent of the [Usage] Panel
66% من لجنة "الاستخدام"
found it unacceptable in 1988,
وجودها غير مقبولة في عام 1988،
58 percent in 1999,
و58% عام 1999،
and 48 percent in 2011."
و48% عام 2011".
Ah, the Usage Panel,
لجنة الاستخدام،
that trusted body of language authorities
ذلك الجهاز الموثوق من السلطات اللغوية
who is getting more lenient about this.
الذي يصبح رحيمًا أكثر بشأن هذا.
Now, what I hope you're thinking right now is,
ما أتمنى أنكم تفكرون به الآن هو،
"Wait, who's on the Usage Panel?
"انتظر، من الذين على رأس لجنة الاستخدام؟
And what should I do with their pronouncements?"
وماذا عليّ أن أفعل بآرائهم؟"
If you look in the front matter
إذا نظرت إلى مقدمة
of American Heritage Dictionaries,
قواميس أميريكان هيرتيج
you can actually find the names
بإمكانك أن تجد بالفعل أسماء
of the people on the Usage Panel.
الأشخاص في لجنة الاستخدام.
But who looks at the front matter of dictionaries?
ولكن من ينظر إلى مقدمة القواميس؟
There are about 200 people on the Usage Panel.
هناك حوالي 200 شخص في لجنة الاستخدام.
They include academicians,
هم يضمون أكاديميين
journalists, creative writers.
وصحفيين وكتاب مبدعين.
There's a Supreme Court justice on it
هناك محكمة عدل عليا ترأسها
and a few linguists.
بالإضافة إلى بعض علماء اللغة.
As of 2005, the list includes me.
في 2005، كانت القائمة تضمني.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Here's what we can do for you.
هذا ما نستطيع فعله من أجلكم.
We can give you a sense
بإمكاننا أن نعطيكم إحساسًا
of the range of opinions about contested usage.
بنطاق الآراء بشأن الاستعمال المتنازع عليه.
That is and should be the extent of our authority.
هذا هو ويجب أن يكون نطاق سلطتنا.
We are not a language academy.
نحن لسنا بأكاديمية للغة.
About once a year, I get a ballot
مرة في السنة تقريبًا، أستلم ورقة اقتراع
that asks me about whether new uses,
تسألني فيما إذا كانت الاستخدمات الجديدة،
new pronunciations, new meanings, are acceptable.
الألفاظ الجديدة، المعاني الجديدة، مقبولة.
Now here's what I do to fill out the ballot.
الآن هذا هو ما أفعله لأملأ الورقة.
I listen to what other people are saying and writing.
أستمع إلى ما يقوله الأشخاص الآخرين وما يكتبونه.
I do not listen to my own likes
لا أستمع إلى إعجاباتي الخاصة
and dislikes about the English language.
وما أكرهه بشأن اللغة الإنجليزية.
I will be honest with you:
سأكون صريحة معكم:
I do not like the word "impactful,"
لا أحب كلمة "إمباكتفل"
but that is neither here nor there
ولكن تلك الكلمة ليست هنا ولا هناك
in terms of whether "impactful" is becoming common usage
من ناحية كونها أكثر شيوعًا
and becoming more acceptable in written prose.
وكونها تصبح أكثر قبولًا في النثر.
So to be responsible,
لذا حتى أكون مسئولة،
what I do is go look at usage,
ما أفعله هو القيام بالنظر إلى الاستخدام،
which often involves going to look
وهو ما يتضمن غالبًا الذهاب للنظر إلى
at online databases such as Google Books.
قواعد بيانات على الإنترنت مثل كتب جوجل.
Well, if you look for "impactful" in Google Books,
حسنًا، إن بحثت عن "إمباكتفل" في كتب جوجل،
here is what you find.
هذا ما ستعثر عليه.
Well, it sure looks like "impactful"
إنها تبدو بالتأكيد مثل "إمباكتفل"
is proving useful
تثبت أنها مفيدة
for a certain number of writers,
لعدد معين من الكتاب،
and has become more and more useful
وقد أصبحت مفيدة أكثر وأكثر
over the last 20 years.
خلال العشرين عامًا الماضية.
Now, there are going to be changes
الآن، ستحدث هناك تغيرات
that all of us don't like in the language.
في اللغة لا تعجبنا جميعًا.
There are going to be changes where you think,
ستحدث هناك تغيرات حيث تعتقد،
"Really?
"حقًا؟
Does the language have to change that way?"
هل على اللغة أن تتغير بتلك الطريقة؟"
What I'm saying is,
ما أقوله هو،
we should be less quick
علينا أن نكون أقل تسرعًا
to decide that that change is terrible,
في الجزم أن ذلك التغيير مريع،
we should be less quick to impose
علينا أن نكون أقل تسرعًا في فرض
our likes and dislikes about words on other people,
إعجاباتنا وكرهنا للكلمات عند الناس الآخرين،
and we should be entirely reluctant
وعلينا أن نكون معارضين بالكامل
to think that the English language is in trouble.
للتفكير بأن اللغة الإنجليزية في مأزق.
It's not. It is rich and vibrant and filled
إنها ليست كذلك، إنها غنية ومتحمسة ومليئة
with the creativity of the speakers who speak it.
بإبداع المتحدثين الذين يتكلمون بها.
In retrospect, we think it's fascinating
باستعراض الماضي، نعتقد أنه من المدهش
that the word "nice" used to mean silly,
أن كلمة "نايس" كانت تستخدم لتعني غبي،
and that the word "decimate"
وأن كلمة "دسيميت"
used to mean to kill one in every 10.
كانت تستعمل لتعني قتل شخص كل عشر دقائق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We think that Ben Franklin was being silly
نعتقد أن بن فرانكلين كان يتغابى
to worry about "notice" as a verb.
بالقلق على "نوتِس" كفعل.
Well, you know what?
حسنًا، تعرفون ماذا؟
We're going to look pretty silly in a hundred years
سنبدو أغبياء قليلًا في غضون مئة سنة
for worrying about "impact" as a verb
بسبب قلقلنا على "إمباكت" كفعل
and "invite" as a noun.
و"إنفايت" كاسم.
The language is not going to change so fast
لن تتغير اللغة سريعًا
that we can't keep up.
بصورة لا نستطيع اللحاق بها.
Language just doesn't work that way.
إن اللغة لا تعمل بهذه الطريقة.
I hope that what you can do
آمل أن ما تستطيعون فعله
is find language change not worrisome
هو إيجاد تغيير باللغة ليس مقلقًا
but fun and fascinating,
بل هزليًا وساحرًا،
just the way dictionary editors do.
بالضبط كما يفعل محررو القواميس.
I hope you can enjoy being part
آمل أن تستمتعوا بكونكم جزءً من
of the creativity that is continually remaking
الإبداع الذي يعيد باستمرار صناعة
our language and keeping it robust.
لغتنا ويحافظ على نشاطها.
So how does a word get into a dictionary?
إذن كيف تدخل كلمة ما إلى القاموس؟
It gets in because we use it
إنها تدخل لأننا نستخدمها
and we keep using it,
ونستمر باستخدامها،
and dictionary editors are paying attention to us.
وينتبه محررو القواميس إلينا.
If you're thinking, "But that lets all of us decide
إذا كنتم تفكرون، "ولكن هذا يجعلنا جميعًا نقرر
what words mean,"
ما تعنيه الكلمات"
I would say, "Yes it does,
سأقول، "نعم، إنها كذلك
and it always has."
وقد كانت دومًا كذلك"
Dictionaries are a wonderful guide and resource,
إن القواميس هي دليل ومصدر رائع،
but there is no objective dictionary authority out there
ولكن ليس هناك سلطة قاموس موضوعية في الخارج
that is the final arbiter about what words mean.
تكون الحكم الأخير بشأن ما تعنيه الكلمات.
If a community of speakers is using a word
أن يستعمل مجموعة من المتحدثين كلمة
and knows what it means, it's real.
ويعلمون ما تعنيه، فإنها حقيقية.
That word might be slangy,
من الممكن أن تكون عامية،
that word might be informal,
من الممكن أن تكون غير رسمية،
that word might be a word that you think
من الممكن أن تكون كلمة تعتقد بأنها
is illogical or unnecessary,
غير منطقية أو غير ضرورية،
but that word that we're using,
ولكن تلك الكلمة التي تستخدمها،
that word is real.
تلك الكلمة حقيقية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)